Yalan (Christina) Bi

164 E. University Dr. Apt J102, Auburn, AL 36832 christinabi123@gmail.com • +1 (334) 728-1405 • https://christinabi.github.io

SUMMARY

Experience with lithium-ion battery electrochemical and equivalent circuit modeling, optimal charging strategy design, and online SOC/SOH estimation. Complete multiple projects in the past 5 years with hands on experience of large experimental data set processing and battery-in-the-loop testing.

EDUCATION

Auburn University, Auburn, AL

• Doctor of Philosophy in Mechanical Engineering

May 2015 - May 2020

- o GPA: 3.93 / 4.00
- Thesis: Online state and parameter estimation of lithium-ion batteries based on a reduced-order electrochemical life model
- Master of Science in Mechanical Engineering

Aug 2014 - Aug 2018

o GPA: 3.93 / 4.00

Jilin University, Changchun, Jilin, China

• Bachelor of Science in Automobile Engineering

Sep 2010 - Jul 2014

o GPA: 3.38 / 4.00

EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant, Auburn University

Collaborated with companies (GM, LG Chem, Hyundai, etc.) on multiple projects. Responsible for meeting arrangement and progress report development

• Online SOH Estimation Using Nonlinear Filters and ML Methods

Aug 2018 – May 2020

- Estimated SOH and parameters using particle filter via a physics-based aging model
- Analyzed sensitivity of terminal voltage and SOC analytically with respect to aging parameters
- Applied machine learning methods with aging models for parameter and SOH estimation
- Collaborated with materials-majored students on conducting postmortem analysis of battery cells
- Characterization of Heat Generation in Large-Format Pouch Cells

Oct 2018 - Oct 2019

- Designed a calorimeter with Kalman filter for heat generation rate measurement
- $\circ\,$ Developed a cell surface temperature control algorithm working simultaneously with the calorimeter
- $\circ\,$ Worked closely with team members and provided guidance to control/estimation-related problems
- Development of an Ultra-fast Charging Algorithm for a High Power Battery
 May 2017 Feb 2019
 - Developed a ROM considered the SEI layer formation and lithium plating/stripping
 - $\circ~$ Validated model using data of a large-format NMC622 cell and achieved 22 mV maximum error
 - Evaluated sensitivity of electrochemical parameters and procedure for parameter estimation
 - Designed an adaptive SPKF with equality constraints for SOC estimation with 2% maximum error
 - Applied pulse charging to promote lithium stripping to reduce both charging time and aging rate
 - \circ Led a team of 3 graduate students; planned and organized monthly meetings with sponsors and completed project 3 months in advance
- Development of a ROM and Online Monitoring Algorithm for an LFP Cell
 May 2015 Dec 2017
 - Developed and validated a ROM for an LFP cell with modeling of side reactions
 - Designed an EKF for SOC estimation with 3% maximum error and tested it in a BIL system
 - Conducted tests on self-constructed test-stations controlled by LabVIEW; conducted EIS tests to evaluate changes in aging parameters of ECM
 - Collected and processed a large amount of data collected at different operation conditions

Graduate Teaching Assistant, Auburn University

- Guided and trained new graduate assistants
- Created and graded assignments, projects, and exams
- Instructed students with Mechatronics laboratory exercises and software training

SKILLS

- Matlab/Simulink (+5 years), Python (+4 years), LabVIEW (+4 years), Git, LaTeX, Mathematica
- Applied machine learning and deep leaning with Scikit-learning and Keras
- Ability to communicate effectively both as a leader and a team member

PUBLICATIONS (SELECTED)

- [1] Y. Bi, and S-Y. Choe, "An adaptive sigma-point Kalman filter with state equality constraints for online state-of-charge estimation of a Li(NiMnCo)O₂/Carbon battery using a reduced-order electrochemical model," *Applied Energy*, Jan 2020.
- [2] <u>Y. Bi</u>, X. Zhao, and S-Y. Choe, "A hybrid state of charge estimation method of a LiFePO₄/graphite cell using a reduced order model with an extended Kalman filter," in *2019 American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, PA, Sep 2019
- [3] Y. Bi, and S-Y. Choe, "Automatic estimation of parameters of a reduced order electrochemical model for lithium-ion batteries at the beginning-of-life," in 2018 IEEE Vehicle Power and Propulsion Conference (VPPC), Chicago, IL, Aug 2018
- [4] X. Zhao, <u>Y. Bi</u>, and S-Y. Choe, "An integrated reduced order model considering degradation effects for LiFePO₄/graphite cells," in *Electrochimica Acta*, 280, pp.41-54, Aug 2018

AWARDS & SCHOLARSHIPS

• Graduate Research Assistantship, Auburn University

• Graduate Teaching Assistantship, Auburn University

• Second Prize Scholarship (top 10%), Jilin University

• Third Prize Scholarship (top 15%), Jilin University

May 2015 – May 2020

May 2018 - May 2020

Aug 2013 – May 2014

Aug 2010 – May 2013

LANGUAGES

Chinese: Native English: Proficient